whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases
I see these as collaborations and so if
this is not something that you weren't
published then we're in the same boat
with respect to that it's probably a
more elegant way to say that but but
it's it's kind of even that point itself
is an interesting place for departure
actually yeah because in a conversation
I think you had with Jordan Hall I think
it was with Jordan you mentioned a
really interesting distinction between
vulnerability and exposure that was
something that came up as particularly
alive in that conversation and that was
something that immediately struck a
chord with me and I think it's I think I
fight I just think it's extremely
profound and so I've been thinking about
it quite a lot and I'd actually really
like to ask you about it but given that
I certainly want to hear your response
and have that as part of the recording
I'd also like you as well maybe perhaps
first just to briefly introduce yourself
and how you feel most alive showing up
in the world at the moment so that yeah
our listeners can get a sense of a
little bit of who you are well what's
calling my what's calling me most alive
in this moment is wanting to know
whether or not you got a haircut I did I
didn't get a haircut
yeah yeah in a bit with the headphones
but is it natural like that yeah curly
yeah is it curly am i synchro yeah yeah
there's coast there's coast there yeah
no it's I mean it's obviously been cut
but other than that it's it's natural
yeah yeah yeah thank you I had
difficulties with my hair for many years
it took I don't think I had a care in
the world from until about the age of 11
and then between the age of 11 and 23 24
even I could say you I could say I cares
I cared quite a lot but did not know did
not know what the hell to do about that
well I should be able to manage this one
now I think I think this is I think
that's the level of that's the level of
self concern in that vain way that if I
couldn't presence that one I still feel
like all right I feel a little bit of
something there but it's like you know
what that's just how it is
I've figured it out now I've got a
product I can get a haircut put some
headphones on I used to wear a hat every
day basically I used to wear a hat every
day I read Jeep when I was in my early
twenties I loved it in you know I'm in
Arizona but I was also like just growing
out my hair now I have like Spiral
golden locks and I had no idea I had
curly hair until I let it because I'd
never let grown before but man it was a
commitment to get to that in-between
period because I wouldn't I'd be you
know like I'm in my early 20s so I'm
like a walking testosterone like machine
and like mmm told you know all that's it
it's the right combination and gel and
stuff so it didn't look to it and then I
go to my Jeep and I Drive down the
street and I look at it look like bozo
[Laughter]
I like how you weren't aware you had
curly hair that seems that seems almost
a ludicrous situation how old were you
when you discovered I was like in my
early twenties basically yeah Wow 80
like but I had no idea for these perfect
spiral curls people yet Bobby oh there
you go
I see that you know I was all like I was
kind of buffed out and I was a
bodybuilder when I was younger and like
yeah and so I just people just didn't
quite know what to make for this this
one here in ordered ah yeah mm-hm
well Fabio is quite a meme I mean that's
why I said that fuck I don't know I
don't even have an image of what he
looked like
but even growing up I remember somehow
that man's name became somewhat
synonymous with like ultimate stud of a
man but also with a hint of you're
trying a bit too hard
totally yeah yeah it's like I think if
you you know I don't know much about him
either yeah but there is it sense of
like if you were to shape yourself in
exactly the prototype of what men think
women want you'd probably call you like
a 1 version of like what would look good
and what is good but you'd also imbued
with is all the mistakes that men
inherently see the big yeah right right
right
God attraction is so interesting yes
what came to my mind there is smell
because like there are people who at
various times would not enjoy smelling
me but the strange thing is is that
there's a select few number of people
who enjoy smelling just that kind of
smell and I'm like what what yeah what
is going on there yeah yeah I have no
idea yeah no idea but that we are man
like I don't I think the essence of a
fetish right it's just that where it's
almost like the opposite of allergic
reaction where it's like you're there's
something benign then it responds to as
like just like by getting sick or
defending its own I think it's almost
the opposite of like where you have like
these these peculiar things that become
almost religiously profound for people
mmm yeah and I wonder about how
difficult those early steps were into
fully accepting that and realizing that
as profound may be the kind of
resistance both as a as you know felt
in that kind of super-ego away from the
from the social world right and then
also maybe in an intimate relationship
and also coming somehow from within
I can I can sense myself reaching for a
pattern that's maybe just before its
time but it does make me think of the
exposure and vulnerability element just
a little bit yeah
there's something about there's
something about presencing your
authenticity in a manner in a setting
where that is held and you know
energetically transmitted transmuted and
communicated back to you that's
fundamental to there being a sort of
productive and appropriate growing
relationship to the presencing of that
authenticity and of course if it's not
might feel exposed unsafe more walls
might come up but I really would I
really would be very interested in
hearing hearing you reflect on that
distinction between vulnerability and
exposure and maybe how you felt when
that came to you recently in that
conversation you had well this actually
kind of speaks to I mean this is an
interest way in just just introduce sure
so I am because that a lot of this has
just been what by dwelling and doing
which is if you look at the a lot of
circling is about is about really being
with the other and a big part of it has
to do with being seen and being heard
and being felt and then all of the
complications and the beautiful things
that come up with that I thou connection
right and so I mean it's just
fascinating to watch what happens to
somebody in different ways when they
become aware that they're paid attention
to
mm-hmm if you think about it's like it's
it's just an interest it's such a it's
it and I don't have anything figure it
out here
I think I found a mystery in that that
if I follow it all the way I end up like
in some interesting almost religious
kinds of places yes yeah yeah I I feel
truly that that the path leads that way
yeah yeah what a dope curious what is it
what is it you think that spoke to you
that had it stand out right what's the
thing that because you knew this is one
of the things I'm curious I'm always
interested in those things where it this
is the big kind of phenomenological
mystery to me is how how do I know um
cuz you find out when something grips
you right mm-hmm but how do you know
without knowing what it is right already
you'd be gripped by it and look at like
if I look at my life those things that
have really seized me right ice are the
things that have ended up being those
things in my life that have been the
most self revealing character building
the things I'm the most proud of and
also was simply the process of finding
out what it would actually gripped me
was like a phone always like op they has
a horizon of something beyond the
horizon mm-hmm
as I move it it gives more above ground
but it doesn't ever release to beyond
the horizon because he can't reach it
what what is what is it that grips you
and I sense that something out of the
horizon of all these kind of wild
conversations posting something about
you I'm just curious what what what do
you think it was well well
many things interesting many things
gripping and I know it to be true is
what comes up to me right it's like yes
it's and I know it to be true from
multiple perspectives and I know it to
be true from many embodied experiences
and I know it to be true in my future
because I also I see it as a as a
fundamental dynamic enabling of
communication transformation and growth
itself yeah so it's a fundamental cog
you know and what's interesting is that
and I really love the horizon metaphor
you use I've I've and how you make the
point you just made and communicate that
feeling and that inquiry it's something
I've heard you communicate a few times
before and when we spoke to each other a
month and a couple months ago now it was
something you presents then and it it
impacted me and I find that it is a
really really beautiful way to
communicate something about the
revelatory but never complete revelation
of mystery and the transformation of our
selves
well what also strikes me is that
there's a sense in which we know and a
sense in which we don't know there's an
awful lot in it in almost it may be it
depends on on how on what kind of box
we're looking to
wrap around that initial sense of
knowing because I suppose in some sense
that you're oriented towards the horizon
at all is a critical part of the actual
knowing of the directionality that's
appropriate itself so it's precisely as
it should be it is the like what else do
we want other than other than meaningful
orientation in a more appropriate
direction we might want a few other
things but at some level you know that
made that that's that's a beautiful
thing to be in touch with yeah yes and
what is it and it's like you know the
sense of it was I really like what you
just you pointed out was this a kind of
it because it brings along the
primordial sense of it wearing in order
for a what is beyond the horizon to it
to lay claim to me right or to be
claimed by it or to claim it
I must already in some sense be in
relationship to it mm-hmm
and that whatever that is right that
before I have any before I can know
about anything there's already a
anything is available to me in some way
that I find myself not necessarily
having but existing of and that that
sense of that sense of crime or reality
right is where I think this that where
what makes wonder wonder write this
wonder isn't that sense of just the
fantastical but it's more like wonder is
that sense where she heard somebody
really brilliantly put it like this and
thinking about it ever since and
actually I think you were there when I
showed up that that at the sense making
wormhole
well which is really somebody said he
talked about wonder
is being in a room and then all of a
sudden like leaning back and then
realizing that that wall actually was a
door and if you open definitely and it's
like gone through the door yet but just
that feeling of things that were already
there right that were ordinary were can
feel that moment of unveiling of what is
most near hmm it's such a beautiful
notion and the that line of expression
is something that I feel I've run
through in slightly different words
before and and it's the kind of thing
that's of a depth that would find many
many many artistic representations
because I think it's something that is
it's it's I don't know I don't I don't
think life is possible
without that being the case because
we're always precisely where we are
right and if if it's not within your if
there is not some capacity to discern
immediately from where you are in some
way then there's like a deep
discontinuity that I could only
associate with a kind of death that
maybe that maybe you don't come back
from and you know there are deaths that
we seemingly come back from used
metaphorically you know but then as well
I'm not really sure what death is to be
honest with you yeah well it's like I
think I was having a moment just kind of
sinking into both what you were saying
but also like to to the way that I
experience you in that moment but also
I've experienced throughout is like how
things really hit you mm-hmm like a
sense of just like
like and this kind of gets back to the
the sense what I think I think those
moments for you to me those are moments
of vulnerability right where there's a a
it seems to be a cultivated openness
that you it doesn't seem like you choose
to have it in some decision oriented way
but there's a place that you sit that
you're that you're proactively open to
be hit by what you don't know that you
don't know yet but you know enough to be
oriented around it to be struck by it
and I I think I perceive that those
moments of in it and I think it comes
across in a lot of its the intensity of
your expression and the way they find
out what you're saying a second after
you say it like there's a there's a
there's a risk there and I would imagine
like just the awareness of that this is
being watched by other people and that
there's there's an orientation towards
that risk that I would imagine it you
are enacting a certain kind of proactive
[Music]
vulnerability which i think is what
makes something vulnerable is that it's
the the distinction that we're talking
about is so people that don't know what
we're talking about is is that the
difference between exposure and vault
and vulnerability has to do with being
being a volunteer right it's about
volunteering just say the thing right
that I know that if it isn't received or
it's not understood that I will in fact
feel pain right mm-hmm
whereas whereas exposure is this
experience of what where I think a lot
of our traumas come from right which is
you're going along you're in the school
yard and then you know somebody
maliciously comes up behind you like
pulls your pants down and everybody
looks at you there's there's no agency
in that there's
like being a defected being exposed
mm-hmm but now if you think about it
he's like if you challenge yourself to
like I'm gonna go out to that same place
in front of those people and pull my
pants down and tolerate that whole
experience you could imagine that being
growth full right almost right good sure
sure
yes different thing that's kind of like
woman like that that's the distinction
they were talking about mmm yeah I think
that's I think it's a really I think
it's a really beautiful distinction
mm-hmm and I also feel that what you say
your observation observation about me is
true as well
although the choice as to whether or not
I am doing it is an interesting one I
can remember and still from time to time
although to be honest with you quite
rarely into environments where my at
least a certain degree of my expression
is not appropriate and I feel very much
just what I'm just what that leaves of
me in relationship with that person if
that's the case and I'm not just talking
about you know having a chat with
someone at the supermarket it's not like
I meet them and just want to drop into
some existential not knowing right it's
not like that at all but you can have a
laugh and you can just be more present
still and that's appropriate and you can
have just the little dance with this the
little vulnerabilities opening up the
world of expression between the two of
you and maybe for just a moment there's
a little bit of a joyfulness there I'm
not talking about those instances of
feeling like it's not appropriate for me
to express but but when when you're
suppose there's instances in which you
you feel that there are areas where
someone else might not be willing to go
and there's there's lots of those and
I'm not again saying that that's not
appropriate but there's something about
when someone
doesn't want to go somewhere in such a
way that compromises that authentic
development of that relationship the ex
the experience of that is something I am
attendant to and I feel very much as
though remaining in the bondage of that
serves neither myself nor them now
context dependent sometimes things play
out over longer periods of time not
trying to be moralistic about this or in
any way but the point being I am I can
remember and feel in touch with what it
is to not in fact step forward and speak
on the tip of your tongue because
there's actually a deep I feel there's a
deep knowing here that's before and
between and after the words that in fact
we're sharing right now right so even
though proposition II I'm not quite
aware of what we will discuss in some
sense I've I've already invested
entirely voluntarily a certain dignity
and trust in this relationship and that
that automatically unlocks a place
within me and you because I sense it's
reciprocal that opens us in fact if some
deep a structural but but qualitative
realities of the way relationships can
be and oh look life is this weird
complex thing that's also very simple
depending on just how it strikes you and
where you're at and what it feels like
to be there you know and there's this
sense I get that some of the deepest
wisdom and self-realization and wonder
and so much of what we seek in mac maybe
all of what we seek is in some sense
precisely or is already there it's just
you're you're looking to put a box
around what it is before in fact it
presences itself
over durations that extend beyond what
your view of a box is capable of holding
but it shouldn't be boxed it is just to
be something like that yeah yeah I was
just aware of just as you're talking
just the sense of sinking in with you
right there is a very distinctive sense
of like like oh we're in this together
wait and I think it was maybe hmm
I was already experiencing it but not
explicitly and tell you what you said
and I sense this with you right like in
some level I'm already shows in the
direction that we're in and I sense this
with you it's not like there's a trip
what I'm hearing is that there's a trust
there all right like like if he didn't
sense it with me
like maybe nothing like maybe like you
had a sense of like where I was actually
like waiting to get you on something or
something like that right or there
wouldn't be this trust and I was feeling
the relationship just sinking into
myself and a willingness to be
vulnerable or willingness to not know
where we're going to like let go of
boxes and when he said that I was like
oh I was already inside of that when he
said it just highlighted it for me know
that kind of quality of I think we can
engender there that there's a there's a
there's a sense of of that where we're
doing something together and we're we
both we don't know where it's going but
there's a you I get the sense that I can
kind of fumble fuck my way through
something right and then I realize I'm
sitting my pants down I don't even know
where we are and you're gonna be like
right like and
yeah there's a sense of but it's not a
truck like I know you or I know
something about you like it's not like I
have you pegged or I have guarantee of
something right it's more like we're
engaging it's more of us as more of a
sense of that there's a way that we're
sharing there's a way of acting that
we're both sharing that seems to
engender a quality of enactment within
my own nervous system that I can feel
mm-hmm and I look what it is is just I
think it's honoring this sense in which
where vulnerability comes from its from
the voluntary sense which i think is
courage one of the things I've noticed
in one of these I've just seen over and
over and over again and and experienced
it in in encircling and teaching people
and discovering what circling is is that
there's when somebody's being genuinely
courageous it's almost impossible to not
be totally gripped and moved by that
there's something about there's
something about a shared courage it's
all it's almost like you could just kind
of take the you know it's almost like to
perceive I'm what I'm wondering about
this as I'm saying it's like to perceive
someone else having courage I think is a
different kind of perception than
perceiving what they're doing or what
they have it's almost like it's a
perception that is invoke some at a move
in this that seems to come from the
center of our being and perhaps
and perhaps that is what that's the
virtue and vulnerability is courage and
just what that opens up yeah yeah the
potential that that enables to to come
forth to me and to be connected somewhat
so that there's because I suppose if we
think about some some line of expression
some improvisational dance some dialogue
some addressing addressing a room of
people really moving forward just bit by
bit there's a sense in which each step
when taken appropriately if that timing
is is held if it's landed then well
there are steps that have come along the
way and there's in fact what has been
created as something that holds you know
so as new things are coming into being
presence there is some some kind of
connectivity security that enables
everyone attendant to that expression to
be to be there somehow and to stand a
little bit there's a place for it least
one of the feet to be grounded right
yeah yes yes the the sense of what I
think I heard you say is basically like
yeah there is a sense in which already
I'm not just expressing but I'm all
aware of the impact on the expression
right so there's a sense there's a sense
of think Jordan Hall put it like this
it's like his memory of when he was a
kid and approaching a cat you had to
really you had to really feel
- what does the can't want it animates
and every part of the expression right
mm-hmm that and that was connected to
that part of the dialogue that I thought
was just so profound it just spun me
around in the chairs we make he said you
know does that mean that the like he
said is it possible the world is
vulnerable but I think I think there's
something so gorgeous around this and I
think it's what you're pointing to which
is we're talking about the it that we're
talking about is our relationship in in
the in in in and how we respond in our
existence in every moment right to
everybody right that were that were in
some kind of intimate and intimate
relation it's not just me acting upon
the world that I I get to that you know
I get to in frame and consume like my
being in that I even imported towards a
world in a horizon at all is already a
response to being as a whole and i thou
kind of relationship and so if we say
that the world is vulnerable that it's
just it's entrusting me right with being
there right with my existence right
we're talking about something really
intimate mmm a deep involvement a deep
involvement yeah yeah yeah absolutely
yeah cats don't fuck about
they don't fuck about when it comes to
having they're having a nice stroke they
don't they they like to come just to the
edge of where your arm can reach yeah
you know I mean they love that they know
they know that they know the arm span of
any human being just by
just by looking for a saying they just
say that you have to you have to reach
you I'll meet you just reaching at the
edge right you have to be you have to be
real good at petting me for me to come
any closer than that you know what it is
to be a human being all Youmans like
fries they may can't not not admire the
cats right I love cats yeah
I love cats yeah I'm looking forward to
seeing my mom's cat at Christmas her
name's Mary Poppins yeah she's a big cat
she's a good cat yeah yeah I'm looking
forward to it there's something there's
something beauty it's beautifully
meditative yeah it's it's like just the
system its aesthetic appreciation and
gentleness and if you ain't
aesthetically appreciating and being
gentle
you're just you're gonna find out about
it very quickly yeah yeah yeah so it's
it's a very it's a very deep notion the
consideration of of the world as
vulnerable that's a very deep notion and
the intimacy point you made that rings
true I feel I can begin to make sense of
it from an intersubjective perspective I
can make sense of it from the
relationality we experience with the
world from my understanding John may use
a term like the trans active trans Jack
t'v to characterize the code defining
interpenetration of growing relationship
the relationship between a cognitive
agent and the environment which itself
is imbuing everything you know in a just
a myriad ways even within that
particular mapping of agent to arena
because we ourselves are comprised of
you know layers and layers of complex
systems that are realizing themselves in
relationship to habitat and just what we
tap into when we begin to quieten and
listen to the world that we're in
relationship with well just what do we
mean by the world fundamentally what
does what do we mean by the world you
know I don't think it necessarily means
just this well and of course it doesn't
just mean some almost 2d pictorial we
might have about country here doing this
to other country right and I'm a citizen
of that country there's it's it's
something so much more fundamental in
the very nature of how our identity
itself transforms and our experience of
just what that is in relationship to
what we care about that's the level it
takes me to begin to presence to to open
open into this kind of exploration yeah
only I I think I'm I'm struck by the the
the the world is a like evoking the
mystery of the world right like that's
uh that's I think that one of the one of
the key points for me that I keep if I
just keep looking at what what as I've
gotten older like what is what is the
what is the thing that's beyond for me
what I've no this is as I as more as I
move towards the horizon of course
horizon is the thing you can't have a
reach right mm-hmm
yet it's a horizon because it also
speaks to beyond it right so there's
this as you move towards it you can kind
of get this sense and like I'm sure like
it for anybody's listening just look at
your own life and look at those horizons
they've called you forward that and then
look at yourself in the mirror and see
see the character
the mirror and then you you're gonna you
start to realize like that character is
very much shaped by these those things
that's calling us forth that we
continually reveal and to me it's it
seems like the measure of what's most
real is that which keeps disclosing its
infinity its sense of mystery and I so I
think that's what spoke to me when you
talked about yeah the world like on one
level the world is the the world is the
only thing we've ever experienced it's
the most ordinary thing in the world
yeah when you look at do you think about
the world what do we mean when we say
world hmm right
like seems like it if you try to point
to it well where is the world like we're
always already in um how Co constitute
at the same time mm-hm
like how I somehow how I'm in it reveals
it in the character that it does yet yet
I was already in it already there's like
so much there's so much mystery mm-hmm
it's a light like that yes mm-hm
that's really beautifully expressed
sometimes we can experience lostness in
the mystery I think perhaps this is why
we don't always move into it and it
strikes me guy because I've listened to
and watched in fact I've watched and
listened to I'd say about seven and ten
conversations you've had maybe maybe
about ten actually there's a few and
other podcasts
well and yeah maybe 10 11 and in a very
short space of time we spoke for a few
hours our first time we've been speaking
now and I knew already and had sensed
and am sensing that which we've already
presence twitch was a certain you know
an unspoken and spoken agreement to be
here on the on the cusp of vulnerability
with each other and I've witnessed a
really remarkable capacity that you have
to enable that in others and I think
that the people I've heard you speak to
our impacting exceptional people who are
entering into that sort of covenant with
you obviously with the capacity to
presence that but I can but eyes I see I
see a mastery in what you do and I and I
also feel that that that you that you
have stepped into that mystery and know
what it is to be on the pulse of it and
also to be lost in it and I feel it has
to be that way otherwise otherwise you
wouldn't be as able as you are to help
stick the landing of where the
relationship goes you know you know in a
way you've you've landed that many times
awkwardly probably you know over the
course of your life to know that it's
okay I'll serve at it in this particular
instance is perfectly acceptable my own
pants down in the in the schoolyards and
still been victim of it
and that's a man that's a that's a deep
thing it's a profound thing yeah yeah
and thank you says thank you for thank
you for your caring I really appreciate
it it's part of what I see is that this
something profound in the capacity you
have that I wish for more people to have
the opportunity to develop and I don't
mean I wish them to become you I mean
that I think you are doing something in
fact that there's something archetypal
about it there's something necessary
with respect to how how a relationship
with the unknown in an inner
relationship can transform in a way
that's in touch with being held and seen
and my sense is that that is a deep part
of this kaleidoscope of conversation and
tentative imagination rere imagination
construction of the frameworks where in
which we can participate the habitats
and frameworks and modalities where in
which we can collectively realize the
the set and the setting to enable
continued transformation of people in a
way that has then be held in community
with each other and yet sovereign it's
it's really fundamental and I just I see
that and it's it's why it's such a I
feel so glad to be having this
conversation with you right now I really
felt like the way you know as I was
listening to the way that you were
feeling your way into what you were
gonna say ray is I felt a very familiar
sense of that
way of feeling into it cuz I'm right you
right like I'm right like with you
feeling into what is this that's
happening like I I'm learning a lot
about myself from these conversations
that I do
this wasn't right and it's not like so
this is kind of what's interesting I and
I also I heard this from Christopher
Christopher I in the in the four-way
conversation I had right up in the in
the left my left cord yes watching a
collaborator of Jamba Vicki's a
brilliant thinker in his own right from
although I hear him express himself yeah
I love that guy I'm just like he is
weaving together like it just is so
naturally lyrical in this technical way
I've just it's just so easy unique ease
unique being and he said something in a
podcast I think with the woman who does
that she has a channel about quality I
think yes yes inequality existence yes
yes mom really good stuff that she's
doing um but she had him on and he was
talking about like his venture into into
this world right that no one really
knows what this world is by the way
internet or game be all these kinds of
things is cell phone awareness of a
there's a this world what is this what's
interesting is that we're a wet there's
a self-awareness to whatever it is and
as something with technology but we're
in the it seems like we're in the middle
of something
mmm-hmm and there seems to be a common
awareness that we don't know what it is
but we sense something and and were
that's part as part of the conversation
and so he jumps into this and and one of
these he said is like huh somehow after
these conversations I'm feeling more of
a sense of legitimacy to being a
philosopher mm-hmm and I was like
mmm-hmm what that I I want to have a mod
again and talk and just talk about that
like I think that there's a link between
there's a there's a link between these
dialogue OSes these these these
conversations right where there's a a
mutual known Inc in something that also
transcends but yet informs the
normativity that's going on between us
it shapes both of us right and that he's
starting to come to himself and see
himself as a legitimate philosopher in
such a way that I'm imagining he it
wasn't even like he was thinking he
wasn't now but now experience of it and
I think that's has something it's very
linked to being seen being heard aging
in these things that kind of brings in a
kind of legitimacy right kind of hurt
like a a sense of a presence of and I'm
I would say that I'm actually I'm
finding a new level of that myself
yes because my intention with doing this
was like that's like because I was
listening to podcasts and stuff like
that and I'm listening to the
interviewers and I was I'm almost
thinking oh my god there's so much were
there we could do something and I didn't
say so I was like okay I'm just gonna
start doing that right um yeah and I was
thinking I want to hit the sweet spot
between like a normal conversation and
circling and I mean I I just wanted to
do that and so mm-hmm
people on but what's ended up happening
is a whole other things being revealed
and I part of it too was this sense of
like oh I would have a conversation with
somebody that I remember this there was
a guy there was a guy who is a he's a
Haida garyun scholar
and we like we had this awesome
conversation and I was so excited to
finally talk to somebody that's read
more Heidegger than I have because I
haven't run why the why the hell I've
been like racking my tongue on this kind
of stuff right yeah Heidegger's got to
sing to you otherwise it's not fun I
reckon and so we have this like awesome
conversation and we get done he's like
whoa like this was this was something
else and hmm you know probably a good
thing I don't have a lot of these son
and I it struck me cuz I think I had an
assumption that somebody like him would
be having conversations like this all
the time right like I just don't didn't
know where they were and that so and I I
remember thinking to myself I was like
wait a minute don't you have these
things all the time with people but
there's a different quality to it mm-hmm
and so and I've been hearing that alone
right and so it had me it's had me go
what is my role here I don't know what
it is but it's being I can feel a new
contours of myself being revealed in a
new context that's having me start to
update my own my own assumptions about
myself and what I'm doing hmm
know exactly what that is but there's
it's interesting it's interesting this
phenomena of where something about the
way that we relate and we interact
together that there's can be
conversations and interactions that
shape things like my own identity is not
formed right and this is an artisan I'm
kind of watching a new level of it for
me with myself it's so interesting
because I've been watching you do that
and I'm getting a look in on you do
in a way that you don't even have on
yourself and your yourse a that these
are happening like there's this new
thing that's all of a sudden popped up
and it's in a way I have maybe the image
I have a view is more of that new thing
that you're becoming dan or the old one
obviously because I just haven't seen
that one
yeah and you you're carrying along all
of some of the old stuff as well so I
can see I feel I see quite a lot with
the role you're playing and where you
will play interesting is it shows up
it's showing up it's showing up in that
more of the Wonder sense because like on
some level I'm not like in the world of
circling and the people that connect
with and something this is what I mean
I've been looking at this and be shaped
by it and wrestling with it all and so
there's a there's a sense of where I
understand my own shape in that world
but then bringing that shape into
another world right who has me my shape
in way it discloses I haven't been
disclosed in the way that I'm being
disclosed other people are saying
there's something that's going on there
that's distinct and impacting me and I'm
like whoa well I think it's this thing
that we have been doing but but I'm
having a relationship with them you know
I feel I feel that maybe there's one of
the things that I especially for Becky
and I have just really been kind of
racking our brains around this right
like kind of in a in a collaborative
sense it just seems to be going on its
own which is I wonder it's like here we
are in this kind of Mont like this
postmodern like we're now in the last 10
years it's become something weird if you
become if you actually go to church
right and you believe like it we're now
in the first time I since I've been
alive where being a Christian and having
those beliefs are so out
side of everyone's pre thematic notions
of what can be real or not it it seems
though that what can happen in a
conversation right seems like it's
almost like there's it's like a
conversation is a place where people
it's one of the few places in the
universe or in our what our current
understanding of reality is relationship
seems to be this place where almost like
we can still be reached by God seizures
right we can still have like like like
responses and self-revealing
and notions of transcendence and
understandings and insights that that
can bypass my bypass my beliefs and my
assumptions about a reality right they
even I can't even I can't deny the
experience of what can happen there and
where that seemed to be available in a
religious setting before right it's less
and less available so I have a feeling
I'm not sure but like I have a feeling
that we are circling around something
here that goes actually way back to the
very beginning of Western history which
is I think was Socrates was on top like
we was had it's at its feet on right
relationships dialectical dialo goes
getting closer to the mystery like
something that you can't put into words
but it's beyond but we can be affected
by it like an in relationship seems to
be a place where we're still our pores
are still open to something like that
that's if being starting to be
recognized and that starts to be having
opening all the other things that about
the world and our relationship to and
spirituality is so much there I think
yes
yes as beautiful articulated and as you
can probably tell like I mean you know
you know I mean in a very a very very
serious way and I've thought through a
lot of how to tentatively there's the
Train yeah there you go well you notice
here you go ah yeah brilliant hmm
there's and I notice there's an
appropriate way to presence how the
kernel of this budding transformation in
relationship dialectic community feeling
process must be you know it it apps it's
it's it it is a circling into culture a
circling forth from culture deep within
us already of course as well I'm also
very interested in sort of structural
conversations about how I see something
like what I feel must be present in our
culture in a way that's linked to this
in order for us to in order for us to
him to in my feeling move towards
something more healthy more authentic
more in touch with ourselves the
complexity around him within us each
other
and yes it's something too it's
something to circle it's something to
circle into with care partially because
the preservation of the act of the not
knowing is it with being with the not
knowing with each other nevertheless
committed to the preservation of that
which is continuous in the not knowing
together which all of a sudden begins to
look a bit like some stable ground to
stand on
you know like that I mentioned before
with just stepping forward step-by-step
leaving breadcrumbs around it so we can
actually kind of you know we're sort of
stable here a little bit frou frou this
time yeah and so there's there's the
actual realizing the importance of being
in it and showing up with it that is
primary like is actually the internal
reality of anything we could talk about
in terms of its extrinsic function in
terms of function in terms of where it
might sit in culture but nevertheless
with this project over the last number
of years it's been something I've been
tenderly moving towards and I feel that
things are coming closer in terms of the
level of the the level of sort of a
public profile of that a public offering
of that then I've previously felt
appropriate to speak forth before and
that as well is part and parcel of where
the conversation online is is is
developing and you know an interlocking
piece of all of this has always been and
is always going to be how we relate to
each other there media really isn't that
happens at least as far as I'm concerned
at the moment in time and space so if
there's a certain amount of organization
that has to be directed to create what's
going to happen in tai bird's face it's
like you know our twitter interaction is
essentially kind of
just like a formal structural thing it's
like we're about to launch off somewhere
let's see how fewer characters we can do
that it's like but without that it
wouldn't be happening
yeah and that's just a communication
between the two of us the reality of
course is that there are billions of
people in the world and the coordination
thereof and again it doesn't have to be
it's it with the challenges top-down
coordination of that is not it's not
quite appropriate right yeah so it's
it's how to it's how to make an offer
and it's how to extend an invitation
that is that is nothing more than how
come as you feel and I I truly want you
to come or not come in in some sense
this the same way of your own integrity
and choice yeah right if you don't come
like that there's a sense in which I
don't act I'm not quite sure that I want
you to be there but there's nothing
really more to that other than the
necessary beginnings for well in this
case a certain not even a peer-to-peer
developmental relationship because you
know you might not know exactly why
you're drawn but hey I feel like yeah
I'm I'm ready to comment you know and
that's fine and maybe want to do more
listening than talking and that's that's
beautiful like the contribution is as
valuable yeah but I feel it I feel I
feel there is I feel there is a deep
need for the kind of re-imagination of
our space of socializing fundamentally
and from that space of socializing like
like an annus an essence of that to be
to be recognized as as something to turn
to because it's if it's built correctly
it's built on an authentic presencing
together and so the world the world that
I
[Music]
have been driven to sea for a long time
is one where that the powerful decisions
you know are made are made on the basis
or one is in a position of power if one
has sufficiently held oneself
accountable to authenticity with other
people right in this deep appreciative
either way and I'm I'm just thoroughly I
just thoroughly do not accept anything
else I cannot be it violates violates me
violates the people I care about it
actually violates the development of the
people who would claim to be making
decisions
there's just no it's not it's not in it
there is there is a there is there are
modes of engaging with reality that are
more conducive to loving development and
the sovereign valuing of the possibility
of life itself you know in others in
yourself and and I am struck by the the
bereft Ness of that manifesting in the
world in positions of ostensible you
know power extensible positions of
authority with people looking at them it
angers me a lot really
mmm-hmm right this day and there's the
part I think what what I as you're
talking about when you said I will not
accept there's like a gathering sense I
got right in that of like where and this
is the other side of authenticity hmm
right now one level there is this deep
sense of I think is like letting
different words you can use for it but
there is a sense of kind of like the
that card talks about glass and height
right this kind of profound letting be
letting being being a letting a be right
that allows being to kind of gather up
in and its
on concealing concealment right has this
kind of sage open this to it and you and
at the same time there's also also a
stand right that's you know what I heard
you say is like yeah there's something
you know in the infinite perspectives
and the infinite things I can pay
attention to their themes like that
there is a place that if I bring my
attention there and when you get down to
it it's kind of like it's not based on
certainty right mm-hmm it's based on
something else I don't know exactly what
that is
I would imagine it's that relationship
between the glass and height and the
breakthrough that that that has one name
a wise feel for where reality is there
where the reality may be then let me
know whether or not I'm on or I'm off
right mm-hmm
a kind of disclosure but there is this
kind of quality where it's like there is
a stand there there is like in the end
that the stand is it allows one to
disambiguate in the face of infinite
ambiguity right that this feeling that
as you as you were we have to close to
open right there there are closures to
be made and that is that is that is very
very interesting given just how much
just how much openness calls for just
how much it requires that there are
closures still is a mmm god it's
difficult and this and this might be you
mentioned post-modernism earlier right
there's a sense there with like oh we've
got to be as open as possible but truly
there is deeply not a presencing of the
groundless ground we can stand on in
this in this conception there is a deep
bereft Ness in the substructure of that
way of viewing the world
Yeah right there's no capacity to close
there's no capacity to stand even for a
moment because the metaphysics to
understand that closure is something
that is it's like oh no that's fixed and
eternal if I closed something you know
it's like a it it doesn't have I don't
think it has the kind of the process
relationality that we're describing it
doesn't have built-in the sovereign
participation in transformation it
doesn't have a notion of an identity
that we share that transforms yeah yeah
yeah absolutely and there is a quality
of there's a quality of and this is
something I gotta say we are really I
would say it's and I'm actually learning
about this a lot in my being married mmm
that which is it's so interesting for me
to be married and I keep I keep feeling
deeply school wired and a lot a lot of
the reasons I'm schooled by it is is
that on one level marriage um like you
know people get married all the time
people been getting married all the time
but I kind of went into it like thinking
about like well this is kind of a
formality you're right like well that
can't they pep into it once it is a
formality it's one that forms and I'm
watching it I'm watching myself be going
like wow I'm really in service to
something that I'm inside of that has a
felt sense of a history to it that's
present that organizes my perceptions
and and there's a and I just get this
sense of that there's a there's a
there's a history like there's a
presence of like there's a presence of a
deep structural history being disclosed
and I being being born in the age that I
am right like is kind of like a classic
secular humanists I've always been
suspect of I've always been suspected of
social norms of any kind like I just
almost like Mitchell I just
I'm now kind of seeing the sense of like
whoa wait a minute here there is like
that something has lasted for generation
after generation after generation
already um if you really see that it's
it survived through all of this you
really look at that it what it wages a
deep respect in my experience then I'm
more I'm waking up to more and more and
more and so authenticity and as we talk
about authenticity you know I think that
I had this idea without even reflecting
on it the authenticity was something
like uniqueness or kind of doing your
own thing or or dancing the beat of a
different drummer but I'm now starting
to think it's actually something
distinctly different and I think I
thought about this this word like author
author write like and I and I get this
sense that it's like it's more like this
offenses more like this it's more like
picking up the concerns that you were
bought the inherited concerns that you
were born into and the roles that you
can't not be in right you tell what what
becomes intelligible to do right is is
is given into this like womb of
intelligibility that you're in it's more
of a sense of like you pick up the book
and you read it you read it so deeply
right all the pictures and the
enactments and you do it so deeply that
at some point you've read it so
thoroughly that the next chapters you
turn you you realize that you're writing
the next the next paragraph you're
writing it as you go but this that whole
period of like deeply deeply being of in
in the world and taking on those
concerns and being responsible and like
humbly learning the authorship is the is
the surrender into that fully and really
making
your own and in a certain sense the the
author and that page is really like you
take the pen from all the previous
authors you gotta earn that great yes
mm-hmm oh that's a lot in what you said
that have to earn it could you could you
say more on this weight on this notion
of earning yeah yeah well I think it's
like one of the things that had me at
had it kind of emerge for me in a moment
was just this you brought brought up
like the post modernist and night
there's all kinds accommodations in post
matza like the it's already an
overgeneralization but like you know the
kind of it's a weird arrogance that i
can relate to right I'm kind of up in a
certain way right which is which is
basically look there's no ground all
there is is inherited stories that whole
the whole thing right the whole thing
and one of the things they don't notice
is that okay so there's there's no
ground there for everything is a dent
and they just put themselves in another
ideology another kind of like hmm can't
escape right in a certain sense we still
here we still end up here yep so what
are you gonna do that that is that's
precisely the thing that's always the
thing with it we're with each other and
some were with each other and and I
think this is what kind of brings back
to the relationship one of the things
about about technology right is and I
think this is why circling is emerged
right in a certain way even like 30 you
know 20 30 years ago if we were it would
have been just made no sense to go like
okay we're gonna create we're gonna
create a private
practice on like basically the
fundamental unit of relationship
let's just let's do it on purpose that
wouldn't have made sense until recently
and I and I've been coming to think
about like well why is why is a moment
at Burning Man with with my friends that
opened up to this profound thing how did
it go from that to all around the world
despite right the pathetic characters
that were doing it wasn't it wasn't I
don't know about that but it was all
accepted in ingest but I don't know it
wasn't through like know how in good
business skills it wasn't through market
show right it will happen emerged on its
own it's like what is it responding to
and I I'm not sure but I've come to this
I at first I was like well maybe it's
the methodology right and but I'm like
you know it takes a lot of Education to
look at what we're doing and distinguish
it from any other human potential
movement thing like it and then and then
I started to look at I started to really
look at social media and I think that
there has been something that's been so
profound and impactful that's kind of
that I don't hear talked about that much
which is they think it started at first
with the answering machine right where
you go back in time there was a point
where there was no answering machine and
when you had to exchange information you
always had to call the person and they
had to answer the phone and you had to
have this weird and ambiguously filled
thing called talking have to happen
right mm-hmm
be like a an information exchange right
mm-hmm but then the first place that
came up was it was the answering machine
where all of a sudden I can actually
kind of relay information without having
to go through the the relationship we
can connect without having to relate
now you fast-forward and you look at all
the multiple ways in which we can
connect and exchange information without
having the as Lebanon say the
phenomenological basis of all all
morality and all ethics being the
encounter with the other the ethical
obligation the phenomenological sense of
nervousness you feel when you look at
another's face and why you can't be like
why when you don't have to deal with
that you have road rage and you can do
it without feeling guilt about it right
he's because one thing that happens in
the encounter that is you can't get
below and 11 oz would say that that if
if he didn't have that fundamental
experience of not a sense of a sense of
responsibility hmm
in the face of the other right um epics
wouldn't make any sense unless there was
that primordial mmm relationship and now
if you if you make it an option all of a
sudden to either have that or to send a
text right now have a choice that we've
never had before right and whenever you
change the structure of communication
like like if you you know if you like
read was a McLuhan talks about this he's
like it's so it's it's like whenever you
just change the structured communication
you change everyone's identity you
change the world and so I have a feeling
that in a certain sense of one of the
reasons why circling which the thing
that is unique about circling is that it
it's like you could say isolates the
fundamental unit of relationship that
underlies all of the relationships and
makes it a yoga well
because it's uncomfortable to do that
right my nervous system and of gravitate
towards just like machines did after
Industrial Revolution for
everything in front of us we didn't have
to move right then all before that there
was no such thing called a physical
fitness
right because life was hard enough it
involved lots of movement and I think
that there's a something similar going
on with relationship yeah yeah
definitely definitely so there's that
authentic attunement of of like finding
the cuz that's a lot of what goes on in
interactions on just a social dance one
is we're constantly like if what I say
it kind of hurts you on some level right
or like I mean you get this immediate
feedback that doesn't really there's no
rulebook that lays all that out but it's
a phenomenological enactment of the
dance right mm-hmm
we don't do a lot of anymore because we
can just text each other but I think we
start to lose our humanity mm-hm I mean
these conversations yeah those are some
of the thoughts have been having over
the last couple of years yeah yeah
beautiful thoughts when you mentioned
the word nervousness immediately brought
to mind the nervous system obviously
yeah and how important it is to Co
regulate nervous systems in adults you
know and it's with the text messages
it's you know and we're figuring out new
emojis and gifts and stuff like that but
in many respects it's it's taken pretty
blunt instruments to regulate what is an
incredibly complex complex potential art
form and dance yet and here's
interesting why there's so many places
to go let me check my phone because I
sense okay it's 10:01 and so we have a
my time which means we probably need to
wrap up within about 20 minutes or so
that's right isn't it yes yes yes oh so
interesting there are
would be well okay so this this isn't
this isn't where came up to me to
explore with you until right until the
end of of your expression there and
that's this which is we know that
Millennials and I think even more over
the gen Z which is their the generation
to come after the Millennials are
absolutely immersed in developing their
relational sense of self and sense of
other using platforms and this kind of
technological communication that removes
key elements of what we've for the
entire history of humanity used to
regulate our nervous systems which was
other nervous systems in space in
proximity yeah and there are different
ways of thinking about this that I've
heard I've heard some very optimistic
takes which are relevant to bring into
the picture because we must we must I
think be open to the sort of already
this already relationship we have with
technology and just how much the
incentives or this of the system that
we're a part of are the car is already
running and while we may consider
slowing elements of it down even if that
were the case reimagining how we
consider growth in areas of development
and awareness perhaps rather than a
certain kind of materialistic ordinary
economic growth even if we wanted to
have that conversation which is a very
interesting conversation to have the car
is still going to take a certain amount
of time to slow down and if it just
stopped suddenly that would be a real
bloody problem so the cars going
to moving somewhere and so there's a
sense in which it is interesting to
consider what new modes of communication
and relationship are made possible by
these kind of platforms while at the
same time looking to establish a place
where we may remember this this other in
my sense still deeper kind just because
we're so I mean the whole attitude we've
taken to understanding the world and our
bodies is has for the most part always
been through certain boxes that have
obscured a kind of a different take and
we just there's so much mystery there's
so much mystery you know and it's it's
not it's not appropriate to to box that
away and and not not attend to it and
not reimagine it again and continue to
as of course many many people are but
but there's something but I also don't I
mean I guess what I'm searching for here
is what we might say of the the because
I've heard people present something like
oh there could be you know an affordance
of a different kind of language that
maybe actually we can take a certain
kind of state and perhaps use a certain
kind of emoji or a gif to capture that
in such a way that communicates a great
amount of information and has that embed
in a way that's really fast and adaptive
and in many respects we are establishing
so really we artists so if that's the
case we actually wanted the means
established in that must be continuous
with what it is to show up in person as
well right so so while it's appropriate
to create new icons of communication
these we must be we must be enabling a
continuous nosov our relationship to
that up and down the full stack of
relational modalities yes and yeah as
somebody came to me there oh yeah
there's a there's a sense in which
you know I think you're I think you
brought up a good point which is which
is you know like as much as we can we
could look at this and be horrified
right appropriately hmm there's a way in
which there's a way in which there's a
historical movement right that we just
can't piss in the wind of it right
mm-hmm
we can't one of the things about some of
the some of the dialogue around around
climate changes of like that like I I'm
not an expert in any of this and but I
there there is this sense in which I
notice we're I don't think that we have
history in our hands I don't think we
produced history and I don't think we
have it in our hands as an object right
but I think that there was a nurse in it
work loved it right we're historical
like through and through we already are
before we have anything to say about it
there's something happening and like
there's so many what yes okay it's like
the grit will have the greatest
intention and our very way of addressing
the problem can be the problem itself
right and not even know it and have us
be blind to it
there's something else happening right
um and I I think that there's something
about there's something about not like
just something about that not it's not
like I'm gonna ever figure out how did
how to do a different history it's I
think it's more like there's a movement
that commands deep respect in which I'm
a little ant right in free it's trying
to like even doesn't even know to what
degree it's on a tree right
and be just really aware of those of
just that humility which is strangely
concealed in our times and this is what
Heidegger would call you say this is
this is like where are our memorial
sense of being is is kind of we see
technologically right in the sense of
that being is no longer an object over
against a subject it's now all a
standing reserve where we seek to
optimize and extract the energy from it
we don't long we no longer see the Rhine
we see power plants mmm we see
everything as a resource to extract from
and to order in ever evolving and so
what that does technologically and if
you can kind of see it in anything
technological the being of technology
collapses distances right so like the
more than illogical the phone is the
faster it is and you can there's I don't
know why no one can really say why we
need faster phones like at this point
there's a momentum going on right it's a
movement of being and I think what
Heidegger would say is like it's more
like he would say something like you
know it he can't move against it but you
can develop you can seek to develop it
beyond itself and I heard that
Sensibility
that is beautiful yeah I heard that
sensibility in that like and I and I
wonder I have no idea but I wonder if
part of what's happening in these
conversations right and that people are
now having conversations about these
conversations is that technology
actually has brought brought together a
platform that that enables something
very untechnical called a meandering
conversation right in the chair and that
stret net that beams out that beams out
to me
is hmm I think very distinct from a lot
of the other things that technology does
which is just create more technology
here when I can tell you there's no way
we would have ever of talking before but
we're great unite and then stand on the
platform that this creates and such that
we can we can engage in something that's
not collapsing distances right yeah is
interesting you use the metaphor of
standing on the platform almost as
though then to cool across and engage in
a certain kind of relationality enabled
by the platform there's a there's a
there's a there's a dimensionality to
that there's a that's that's a 3d image
and if you know it's it's also something
taking place over time yeah it's very
interesting guy you've I'm so I'm so
grateful for this conversation and I I
have to I have to
yeah the first the first artificial
thing in it is me is me catering to this
time and space thing because yeah
because if I you know obviously there's
there's the River continues meandering
and but but I'm very grateful I'm very
grateful for for this dialogue and if it
feels absolutely appropriate for me to
share it right is that how you yeah so
so that's beautiful and look I in ways
that we I think need not articulate now
I'm looking forward to the future and
the opportunities for collaboration I
hope that has in store yeah and so I I
wish you a wonderful rest of your day
and weekend
and onwards I'll be I'll be watchin on
and enjoying so thank you and on also a
quote and another I just added another
practical note like so I the and I think
more March is wrong at least I start the
next trading program in in the thing
that I do circling so like a mmm I'll
just I'll give you a link for people to
find that if they want we want to pursue
that right yeah so so yeah I be posting
this obviously to the voice Club YouTube
channel and a podcast and so just let me
know send me a link in Twitter or
Facebook we have each other on Facebook
now what links you would like me to post
and I'll attach them on so that's it
yeah you want me to upload this to my
channel too or if that's something
you're interested to do then that's
interesting only yeah yeah sure I'm
happy to have it out there on both both
I'm going to I've recorded myself with a
camera here as well so I'm actually
going to change the image of me on here
to that and but that doesn't need it you
can just go ahead and publish the one
we've recorded here um so the audio
you're hearing from me is coming out of
these headphones rather than this
microphone so the podcast version I'll
be putting this in so that it's a better
listening experience but um but yeah
yeah absolutely
also next time let's talk I want to talk
about your your live events your live
event yes absolutely and that's
precisely what I'd love to collaborate
on and of course we already are we
already are
you know I'm deeply being informed by
all of this and it's really enabling of
creating a certain presence knowing that
not only are we there in the room with
each other but there are people around
the world too who feel the importance
and the relevance of similar things and
it's that kind of communication across
these micro communities that I think is
part and parcel of this whole endeavor
that we're on so
yeah yeah beautiful all right thank you
see well thank you guys thank you all
right mate I'll talk to you soon I hope
you have a beautiful day bye bye bye
whether you're watching on YouTube or
listening as a podcast remember to
subscribe and hit the bell to track
upcoming releases